<item>
<title>Reduce Font Loading Time in My Blog</title>
<link>https://archive.casouri.cat/note/2019/reduce-font-loading-time-in-my-blog</link>
<guid>https://archive.casouri.cat/note/2019/reduce-font-loading-time-in-my-blog</guid>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I use Source Han Serif on my blogs. And it takes ages to load. Source Serif Pro Regular (an English font) has a size of 217 KB. Source Han Serif Regular? 23.6 MB. I have to reduce the size of the font file!
</p>

<p>
Woff2 is said to be a compressed format. Here is the <a href="https://github.com/google/woff2">girhub repo</a>.
</p>
<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-shell">$ git clone --recursive https://github.com/google/woff2.git --depth 1
$ cd woff2
$ make clean all
$ ./woff2_compress /Users/yuan/p/casouri/misc/SourceHanSerifSC-Regular.otf
Processing /Users/yuan/p/casouri/misc/SourceHanSerifSC-Regular.otf =&gt;
/Users/yuan/p/casouri/misc/SourceHanSerifSC-Regular.woff2
Compressed 23613247 to 15551008.
</pre>
</div>
<p>
After converting to woff2 format, the size is reduce to 15.6MB, still too large.
</p>

<p>
Source Han Serif covers a lot of rare glyph. Maybe cutting them out can give me a smaller file. <a href="https://github.com/fonttools/fonttools">fonttool</a> has s subcommand <code>pyftsubset</code> that produces a subset of a font file.
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-shell">pyftsubset ~/p/casouri/misc/SourceHanSerifSC-Regular.otf <span style="color: #489446;">\</span>
           --unicode=0-7f, 3000-303f,4e00-9faf --flavor=woff2
</pre>
</div>
<p>
gives a font file with only ASCII, CJK Unified Ideographs and CJK Symbols and Punctuation, compressed to woff2 format. The reduced size is 10.9 MB. Still not good.
</p>

<p>
I need even less glyph in my font file. For that I find a file with 3500 most used Chinese glyph in it, and pass that to <code>pyftsubset</code>. (you can find the file at <a href="file:///misc/most-used-zh-char.txt">here</a>.)
</p>
<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-shell">pyftsubset ~/p/casouri/misc/SourceHanSerifSC-Regular.otf <span style="color: #489446;">\</span>
           --unicodes=0-7f,3000-303f <span style="color: #489446;">\</span>
           --text-file=/Users/yuan/Desktop/most-used-zh-char.txt<span style="color: #489446;">\</span>
           --flavor=woff2
</pre>
</div>
<p>
This cuts down the size to 1.7 MB. That’s still large comparing to English fonts, but I’m happy with it.
</p>

<p>
No, not really, it’s still slow, but at least it’s faster than before&#x2026; If I want it to load even faster than that, I need to generate font files that only contains the glyph of a particular page. That’s not trivial for a static site.
</p>

<p>
(Update <span class="timestamp-wrapper"><span class="timestamp">&lt;2019-07-22 Mon 14:20&gt;</span></span>)
</p>

<p>
Since the Chinese fonts still takes a while to load even with the compressed size. It is best to display a default system font before the web font is loaded so the user won’t stare at empty spaces. This is done by <code>font-display</code> property. <code>font-display: swap</code> will display default font almost immediately and swap to web font one it is loaded.
</p>

<p>
(Update <span class="timestamp-wrapper"><span class="timestamp">&lt;2021-04-20 Tue 22:54&gt;</span></span>)
</p>

<p>
The previous font I created has some problems, it doesn’t contain punctuation marks and misses some common glyphs. I fixed those issues and the new file is at <a href="file:///note/misc/常用字及符号.txt">here</a>. I also don’t want the font file to contain ASCII characters, so that Latin characters can fall back to my English font. So I also changed the command:
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-shell">pyftsubset ~/p/casouri/misc/SourceHanSerifCN-Regular.otf <span style="color: #489446;">\</span>
           --text-file=&#24120;&#29992;&#23383;&#21450;&#31526;&#21495;.txt <span style="color: #489446;">\</span>
           --flavor=woff2
</pre>
</div>
]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 21:28:00 -0400</pubDate>
</item>
